How many of you have checked your email today?
كم منكم قام بتفحص بريده الالكتروني هذا اليوم؟
Come on, raise your hands.
هيا، ارفعوا أيديكم
How many of you are checking it right now?
كم منكم يتفحصه الآن؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And how about finances? Anybody check that today?
و ماذا عن الشئون المالية؟ هل من أحد تفحصها اليوم؟
Credit card, investment account?
بطاقات الائتمان، حسابات الاستثمار؟
How about this week?
ماذا عن هذا الأسبوع؟
Now, how about your household energy use?
الآن، ماذا عن استهلاك منازلكم من الطاقة؟
Anybody check that today?
هل من أحد تفحص ذلك اليوم؟
This week? Last week?
هذا الأسبوع؟ الأسبوع الماضي؟
A few energy geeks spread out across the room.
بعض المهوسيين بالطاقة منتشرين في هذه القاعة.
It's good to see you guys.
من الجيد رؤيتكم يا شباب
But the rest of us -- this is a room filled with people
و لكن البقية منا -- هذه غرفة مليئة بالناس
who are passionate about the future of this planet,
الشغوفيين بمستقبل هذا الكوكب
and even we aren't paying attention
و نحن حتى لا نلقي بالاً
to the energy use that's driving climate change.
إلى استخدام الطاقة الذي يقود التغير المناخي
The woman in the photo with me is Harriet.
السيدة في الصورة بجواري هي "هارييت"
We met her on our first family vacation.
التقيناها في عطلتنا العائلية الأولى
Harriet's paying attention to her energy use,
"هارييت" تهتم بمقدار ما تستخدم من الطاقة
and she is decidedly not an energy geek.
و هي قطعاً ليست "مهووسة" بالطاقة
This is the story of how Harriet came to pay attention.
هذه هي القصة عن كيف بدأت "هارييت" تهتم
This is coal,
هذا فحم،
the most common source of electricity on the planet,
أكثر مصادر الكهرباء شيوعاً في الكوكب
and there's enough energy in this coal
و يوجد في هذا الفحم ما يكفي من الطاقة
to light this bulb for more than a year.
لتشغيل هذه اللمبة لما يزيد عن العام
But unfortunately, between here and here,
و لكن لسوء الحظ، بين هنا و هناك،
most of that energy is lost to things
معظم هذه الطاقة تفقد لأشياء
like transmission leakage and heat.
مثل التسرب أثناء النقل و الحرارة،
In fact, only 10 percent ends up as light.
في الحقيقة، 10% فقط ينتهي بها الأمر كضوء.
So this coal will last a little bit more than a month.
و بالتالي هذا الفحم سيستمر لما يزيد عن الشهر بقليل
If you wanted to light this bulb for a year,
إذا أردنا أن نشعل هذه اللمبة لمدة سنة،
you'd need this much coal.
نحتاج هذه الكمية من الفحم.
The bad news here is that, for every unit of energy we use,
الأخبار السيئة هنا هي ما يلي، مقابل كل وحدة طاقة نستخدمها،
we waste nine.
نهدر تسعة وحدات.
That means there's good news,
هذا يعني أنه توجد أخبار جيدة،
because for every unit of energy we save,
لأن لأجل كل وحدة طاقة نحافظ عليها،
we save the other nine.
نحافظ على التسعة وحدات الأخرى
So the question is, how can we get the people in this room
إذاً السؤال هو، كيف يمكننا جعل الناس في هذه الغرفة
and across the globe to start paying attention
و حول العالم أن يولوا الاهتمام
to the energy we're using,
للطاقة التي نستخدمها
and start wasting less of it?
و اهدار أقل ما يمكن منها
The answer comes from a behavioral science experiment
الإجابة تأتي من تجربة في علم السلوك
that was run one hot summer, 10 years ago,
التي أجريت في ذات صيف حار، قبل 10 سنوات،
and only 90 miles from here,
و على بعد 159 كم فقط من هنا،
in San Marcos, California.
في سان ماركوس، كاليفورنيا.
Graduate students put signs on every door in a neighborhood,
وضع طالب في السنة النهائية علامة على كل باب في الحي،
asking people to turn off their air conditioning
يطلب من الناس أن يطفئوا مكيفات الهواء
and turn on their fans.
و يشغلوا المراوح
One quarter of the homes received a message that said,
ربع المنازل استلمت رسالة تقول،
did you know you could save 54 dollars a month this summer?
هل تعلم أن بإمكانك أن توفر 54 دولارا في الشهر هذا الصيف؟
Turn off your air conditioning, turn on your fans.
أطفيء مكيفك، شغل مروحتك.
Another group got an environmental message.
مجموعة أخرى تلقت رسالة بيئية.
And still a third group got a message about
و مجموعة ثالثة تلقت رسالة عن
being good citizens, preventing blackouts.
أن يصبحوا مواطنين جيدين، يكافحوا انقطاع التيار الكهربائي.
Most people guessed that money-saving message would work best of all.
توقع معظم الناس أن رسالة المحافظة على النقود ستؤثر أفضل
In fact, none of these messages worked.
في الحقيقة، و لم تنجح أي واحدة من هذه الرسائل
They had zero impact on energy consumption.
كان تأثيرها على استهلاك الطاقة يساوي صفراً
It was as if the grad students hadn't shown up at all.
كان الأمر كأن الطالب لم يأتي على الاطلاق
But there was a fourth message,
و لكن كانت هناك رسالة رابعة،
and this message simply said,
و هذا الرسالة ببساطة قالت،
"When surveyed, 77 percent of your neighbors
"قمنا بالمسح، 77 % من جيرانكم
said that they turned off their air conditioning and turned on their fans.
قالوا أنهم أطفأوا مكيفاتهم و شغلوا المراوح.
Please join them. Turn off your air conditioning
من فضلك انضم لهم، أغلق مكيفك
and turn on your fans."
و شغل مراوحك."
And wouldn't you know it, they did.
و هل تعلمون شيئاً، لقد فعلوا.
The people who received this message
الناس الذيت تلقوا هذه الرسالة
showed a marked decrease in energy consumption
أظهروا انخفاض ملحوظ في استهلاك الطاقة
simply by being told what their neighbors were doing.
ببساطة بإخبارهم بما يفعل جيرانهم.
So what does this tell us?
إذاً، ماذا نستخلص من هذا؟
Well, if something is inconvenient,
حسنا، إذا كان شيء ما غير ملائم،
even if we believe in it,
حتى لو آمنا به،
moral suasion, financial incentives, don't do much to move us --
الضغط الأخلاقي، الفوائد المالية، لا تحفزنا بما فيه الكفاية --
but social pressure, that's powerful stuff.
و لكن الضغط الاجتماعي، هذا مؤثر قوي
And harnessed correctly, it can be a powerful force for good.
و بتسخيره بشكل صحيح، يمكن أن يكون قوة هائلة من أجل الخير.
In fact, it already is.
في الحقيقة، إنه أصلا كذلك.
Inspired by this insight, my friend Dan Yates and I
من وحي هذا التبصر، صديقي دان ياتس و أنا
started a company called Opower.
أسسنا شركة أسميناها قوة أو "أو باور"
We built software and partnered with utility companies
بنينا برمجيات و تشاركنا مع شركات مرافق عامة
who wanted to help their customers save energy.
و التي كانت مهتمة بمساعدة عملائها ليوفروا الطاقة
We deliver personalized home energy reports
قمنا بتسليم تقارير طاقة منزلية مخصصة
that show people how their consumption
و التي توضح للناس استهلاكهم
compares to their neighbors in similar-sized homes.
بالمقارنة مع جيرانهم و منازل مشابهة لمنازلهم من حيث الحجم
Just like those effective door hangers,
تماما كشماعات الباب الفعالة تلك
we have people comparing themselves to their neighbors,
أصبح لدينا أناس يقارنون أنفسهم بجيرانهم
and then we give everyone targeted recommendations
و بالتالي أعطينا الجميع التوصية المستهدفة
to help them save.
لمساعدتهم على التوفير
We started with paper, we moved to a mobile application,
بدأنا بالورق، و انتقلنا إلى تطبيقات الهاتف السيار
web, and now even a controllable thermostat,
الانترنت، و الآن أصبح لدينا أجهزة تنظيم يمكن التحكم بها
and for the last five years we've been running
و خلال الخمس سنوات الماضية كنا نجري
the largest behavioral science experiment in the world.
أكبر تجربة علم سلوك في العالم
And it's working.
و قد نجحنا
Ordinary homeowners and renters have saved
ملاك المنازل العاديون و المؤجرين قد وفروا
more than 250 million dollars on their energy bills,
أكثر من 250 مليون دولار من خلال فواتير الطاقة
and we're just getting started.
و قد بدأنا للتو
This year alone, in partnership with more than 80 utilities
في هذا العام وحده، و بالشراكة مع أكثر من 80 شركة مرافق عامة
in six countries, we're going to generate
في 6 دول، سنقوم بتوليد
another two terawatt hours of electricity savings.
اثنان تيراواط ساعة أخرى من توفير الكهرباء
Now, the energy geeks in the room know two terawatt hours,
الآن، "مهووسي" الطاقة في هذه القاعة يعرفون التيراواط ساعة
but for the rest of us, two terawatt hours
و لكن لبقيتنا، 2 تيراواط ساعة
is more than enough energy to power every home
هو أكثر مما يكفي من الطاقة لتشغيل كل المنازل
in St. Louis and Salt Lake City combined
في كلا مدينتي سانت لويس و و سالت ليك مجتمعتان
for more than a year.
لأكثر من عام
Two terawatt hours, it's roughly half
2 تيراواط ساعة، تقريبا يساوي نصف
what the U.S. solar industry produced last year.
ما أنتجته صناعة الطاقة الشمسية في الولايات المتحدة العام الماضي
And two terawatt hours? In terms of coal,
و 2 تيراواط ساعة؟ بالنسبة للفحم
we'd need to burn 34 of these wheelbarrows
نحتاج أن نحرق 34 من هذه العربات اليدوية
every minute around the clock every day for an entire year
كل دقيقة كل ساعة كل يوم لمدة عام كامل
to get two terawatt hours of electricity.
حتى نحصل على 2 تيراواط ساعة من الكهرباء
And we're not burning anything.
و نحن لا نحرق أي شيء
We're just motivating people to pay attention
نحن فقط نحفز الناس ليهتموا
and change their behavior.
و يغيروا سلوكهم
But we're just one company, and this is just
و لكننا فقط شركة واحدة، و هذا فقط
scratching the surface.
يمس سطح المشكلة
Twenty percent of the electricity in homes is wasted,
20 بالمائة من الكهرباء في المنازل تهدر
and when I say wasted, I don't mean that people have
و عندما أقول تهدر، لا أعني بذلك الناس لديها
inefficient lightbulbs. They may.
لمبات غير فعالة، قد يكون لديهم
I mean we leave the lights on in empty rooms,
ما أعنيه هو أننا نضيء الغرف الخالية
and we leave the air conditioning on when nobody's home.
و نترك مكيفات الهواء تعمل و لا أحد في المنزل
That's 40 billion dollars a year wasted
و هذا يهدر 40 مليار دولار في العام
on electricity that does not contribute to our well-being
على كهرباء لا تساهم في استمرار وجودنا
but does contribute to climate change.
و لكن تساهم في التغير المناخي
That's 40 billion -- with a B --
إنها 40 مليار
every year in the U.S. alone.
كل عام في الولايات المتحدة وحدها
That's half our coal usage right there.
إنه نصف استهلاكنا من الفحم
Now thankfully, some of the world's best material scientists
الآن لحسن الحظ، بعض أفضل علماء المواد في العالم
are looking to replace coal with sustainable resources
يبحثون عن بدائل للفحم مع موارد مستدامة
like these,
مثل تلك،
and this is both fantastic and essential.
و هذا رائع وجوهري
But the most overlooked resource to get us
و لكن أفضل الموارد التي نغض الطرف عنها و التي ستأخذنا
to a sustainable energy future, it isn't on this slide.
إلى مستقبل الطاقة المستدامة، ليس في تلك الشريحة
It's in this room. It's you, and it's me.
و لكن في هذه الغرف. إنه أنتم و أنا.
And we can harness this resource
و يمكننا معاً أن نسخر هذا المورد
with no new material science
بدون علم مواد
simply by applying behavioral science.
فقط بتطبيق علم السلوك
We can do it today, we know it works,
يمكننا أن نفعل ذلك اليوم، نحن نعلم أنه سينجح
and it will save us money right away.
و سيوفر لنا المال فوراً
So what are we waiting for?
إذاً ما الذي ننتظره؟
Well, in most places, utility regulation
حسناً، في أغلب الأماكن تنظيم شركات المرافق
hasn't changed much since Thomas Edison.
لم يتغير كثيراً منذ توماس أديسون
Utilities are still rewarded when their customers
شركات المرافق ما زالت تُكافأ عندما
waste energy.
يهدر عملاءها الطاقة
They ought to be rewarded for helping their customers save it.
يجب أن يتم مكافأتها عندما تساعد زبائنها على توفيرها
But this story is much more than about household energy use.
و لكن هذه القصة أكبر بكثير من استهلاك الطاقة المنزلي
Take a look at the Prius.
ألقوا نظرة على "البريوس"
It's efficient not only because Toyota invested in material science
إنها فعالة ليس فقط لأن تويوتا استثمرت في علم المواد
but because they invested in behavioral science.
و لكن لأنها استثمرت في علم السلوك أيضا
The dashboard that shows drivers how much energy
اللوحة التي توضح للسائق كم من الطاقة
they're saving in real time
يوفر في لحظة استهلاكه
makes former speed demons
جعلت محبي السرعة السابقين
drive more like cautious grandmothers.
يقودون مثل جدات حذرات
Which brings us back to Harriet.
الأمر الذي يعود بنا إلى "هارييت"
We met her on our first family vacation.
التي التقيناها في عطلتنا العائلية الأولى
She came over to meet my young daughter,
لقد حضرت لتلتقي ابنتي الصغرى
and she was tickled to learn that my daughter's name
و قد ضحكت لأنها علمت أن اسم ابنتي
is also Harriet.
"هارييت" أيضاً
She asked me what I did for a living,
و سألتني عن عملي
and I told her, I work with utilities
أنني أعمل مع شركات المرافق
to help people save energy.
لمساعدة الناس على توفير الطاقة
It was then that her eyes lit up.
حينها برقت عيناها
She looked at me, and she said,
و نظرت إلي و قالت،
"You're exactly the person I need to talk to.
"أنت بالضبط هو الشخص الذي أحتاج أن أتحدث معه.
You see, two weeks ago, my husband and I got a letter
كما ترى، منذ أسبوعين، تلقينا أنا و زوجي رسالة
in the mail from our utility.
في البريد الالكتروني من شركة المرافق التي نتعامل معها
It told us we were using twice as much energy as our neighbors."
أخبرونا أننا نستخدم من الطاقة ضعف ما يستخدمه جيراننا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"And for the last two weeks, all we can think about,
" و طوال الأسبوعين الماضيين، كل ما فكرنا فيه،
talk about, and even argue about,
تحدثنا عنه، و حتى تجادلنا فيه،
is what we should be doing to save energy.
كان ما يجب أن نفعله لنوفر الطاقة
We did everything that letter told us to do,
و فعلنا كل ما أخرتنا الرسالة أن نفعله،
and still I know there must be more.
و أنا أعلم أنه ما زال هناك الكثير،
Now I'm here with a genuine expert.
و الآن بما أنني هنا مع خبير أصيل
Tell me. What should I do to save energy?"
أخبرني. ماذا يجب أن أفعل لأوفر الطاقة؟"
There are many experts who can help answer Harriet's question.
هناك العديد من الخبراء الذين بامكانهم أن يجاوبوا على تساؤل "هارييت"
My goal is to make sure
و هدفي هو أن أتأكد
we are all asking it.
أننا جميعاً نسأل نفس السؤال
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)